<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opensourceuniversalremote | alexba.in]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/categories/opensourceuniversalremote/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexba.in/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-13T18:33:54+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexba.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Bain]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alex@alexba.in]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lirc_web v0.3.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2016/03/13/lirc-web-v0-3-0/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-13T11:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2016/03/13/lirc-web-v0-3-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>v0.3.0</code> of <code>lirc_web</code> has just been published to npm.</p>

<p>This release targets mobile optimizations and performance. <code>lirc_web</code> now behaves more like a native app when added to the home screen of a mobile device. A favicon is now shown on the home screen, the URL bar will be hidden from view, and <code>lirc_web</code> will be selectable from the device's multitasking screen. Furthermore, CSS assets are bundled into a single request, small images are now base64 encoded, and an application cache has been introduced to cache all assets locally between requests.</p>

<p>In my testing, with a warm cache, <code>lirc_web</code> now fires a <code>load</code> event within 300ms.</p>

<p>Here's the relevant piece of <code>CHANGELOG.md</code> that describes all updates since <code>v0.2.0</code>:</p>

<pre><code>## [0.3.0] - 2016-03-13

* Adds `grunt-contrib-cssmin` task to combine all CSS requests into one
* Adds ability to set lirc socket in `config.json` (thanks @pmgration)
* Base64 `left-arrow.png` image to reduce a request
* Adds application cache manifest file for offline caching

## [0.2.4] - 2016-01-13

* Extracts macros into a standalone lib/macros.js file
* Adds Favicon (thanks @flochtililoch)
* Adds npm run test:watch action (thanks @OvisMaximus)
* Travis build will now run linter
* Updated dependencies
* Uses local version of jQuery for testing now

## [0.2.3] - 2016-01-03

* Fixing bug where labels were loaded before config (thanks @flochtililoch)

## [0.2.2] - 2016-01-01

* Removing `Makefile` for running tests. Only need `package.json`.
* Fixing .gitignore error for the global lirc_web build

## [0.2.1] - 2015-12-31

* `lirc_web` can now be installed globally and called by `lirc_web` from CLI
* Adding ESLint to the mix and ensuring all JS conforms to Airbnb ES5 standards
</code></pre>

<p>New features are documented in the <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web/blob/master/README.md">README</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lirc_web v0.2.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2015/12/31/lirc-web-v0-2-0/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-31T04:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2015/12/31/lirc-web-v0-2-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <code>lirc_web</code> project (available at <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web</a>) has been updated to <code>v0.2.0</code>, which contains some new features and bugfixes. Here's the summary of the new functionality now available in the project:</p>

<pre><code>[0.2.0] - 2015-12-30

Adding blacklist configuration option to hide unused keys from UI (thanks @OvisMaximus)
Adding support for SSL (thanks @de-live-gdev)
Fixing example config in the README (thanks @de-live-gdev)
Fixes url escaping bug with macros and remotes (issue #23)

[0.1.0] - 2015-12-30

Locking npm versions to ensure future install work
Adding CHANGELOG.md
Adding /refresh link on bottom to reload UI after making changes to LIRC (thanks @f00f)
Adding ability to set custom labels on command and remote names (thanks @elysion)
Adding Apple mobile app capability, disabling zoom (thanks @elysion)
Moving Lato fonts locally to remove external network dependency
</code></pre>

<p>New features are documented in the <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web/blob/master/README.md">README</a>.</p>

<p>On a related note, <code>lirc_node</code> (available at <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_node">https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_node</a>) has been updated to <code>v0.0.4</code>. There's no new functionality in this release, simply locked NPM dependency versions and the addition of a change log.</p>

<p>If you run into any issues with either project, let me know in the comments or (ideally) via the <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web/issues">issues page</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lirc_web v0.0.8]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2014/08/10/lirc-web-v0-0-8/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-10T19:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2014/08/10/lirc-web-v0-0-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I'm going to talk about two features I've added to the <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">lirc_web</a> project. <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">lirc_web</a> is a NodeJS app I wrote that provides a web interface and JSON based API for controlling <a href="http://lirc.org/">LIRC</a>, an open source project that lets you control IR devices from the command line. I built <a href="https://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">lirc_web</a> to run on a RaspberryPi along with an expansion board I designed so that anyone could build their own fully customizable universal remote that is controllable via a web interface from any web connected device (phone, tablet, laptop, smart watch, etc).</p>

<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/universal-remote/lirc_web_v0_0_8.png" height="640px" width="384px" class="center" /></p>

<p>If you'd like additional context about the project, you may be interested in:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://opensourceuniversalremote.com/">Open Source Univeral Remote</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures/">Open Source Universal Remote - Parts &amp; Pictures</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/03/09/raspberrypi-ir-schematic-for-lirc/">RaspberryPi IR Schematic for LIRC</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/02/23/controlling-lirc-from-the-web/">Controlling LIRC From the Web</a></li>
</ul>


<p>In v0.0.8 I've added two new features - macros and repeaters.</p>

<h3>Macros</h3>

<p>Macros allowing you to execute multiple IR commands in rapid succession from a single button tap or HTTP request. The use case for this would be when you need multiple devices to be turned on and set to a certain mode to perform an activity (say, playing a video game or watching a movie). An example macro might be:</p>

<ul>
<li>Turn TV on</li>
<li>Set TV to input 3</li>
<li>Turn receiver on</li>
<li>Set receiver input HDMI2</li>
<li>Turn game console on</li>
</ul>


<p>Macros make performing common multi-step tasks simpler. In addition, Macros are exposed via the API, which means you can execute macros by sending an HTTP request from a growing number of internet of things or web connected devices. For example, you could adjust the volume of the TV from your <a href="https://getpebble.com/steel">Pebble watch</a> or change the TV channel by waving your arm while wearing a <a href="https://www.thalmic.com/en/myo/">Myo armband</a>.</p>

<p>Macros are defined in a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON">JSON</a> configuration file (<code>config.json</code>) that <code>lirc_web</code> expects to find in the root of the project. Here's an example:</p>

<pre><code>{
  "macros": {
    "Play Xbox 360": [
      [ "SonyTV", "Power" ],
      [ "SonyTV", "Xbox360" ],
      [ "Yamaha", "Power" ],
      [ "Yamaha", "Xbox360" ],
      [ "Xbox360", "Power" ]
    ],
    "Listen to Music": [
      [ "Yamaha", "Power" ],
      [ "Yamaha", "AirPlay" ]
    ]
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>macros</code> key is an object of keys (labels) that are set to arrays of <code>[remote, command]</code>  pairs. The <code>remote</code> and <code>command</code> strings should match what is defined in the LIRC configuration file. A small delay is introduced between each command to ensure they are all received.</p>

<p>After you create or change anything in <code>config.json</code>, you will have to restart <code>lirc_web</code>. Afterwards, you'll see your macros listed at the bottom of the user interface.</p>

<p>Macros are also available via the API. You can execute them by creating a POST request to a url like so:</p>

<pre><code>http://ip-of-remote/macros/Play%20Xbox%20360
</code></pre>

<h3>Repeaters</h3>

<p>Repeaters are a type of button that repeatedly send it's command as long as it is held down. The use case for a repeater would be a volume button that should continue to change the volume as long as it's pressed - rather than needing to tap it many times.</p>

<p>Repeaters are also specified in the configuration file. Here's an example:</p>

<pre><code>{
  "repeaters": {
    "SonyTV": {
      "VolumeUp": true,
      "VolumeDown": true
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Similar to macros, the name of the <code>remote</code> and <code>command</code> must match the names you gave these commands in the LIRC configuration file. If you want to change the name of a button, update the LIRC configuration file and restart LIRC / lirc_web.</p>

<h3>Enjoy</h3>

<p>I've found these two features make the <a href="http://opensourceuniversalremote.com/">Open Source Universal Remote</a> significantly more useful for common tasks. If you have any suggestions for new features or ideas on how to improve the project, please share your ideas in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running lirc_web with nginx and upstart]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/11/02/lirc-web-nginx-and-upstart/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-02T09:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2013/11/02/lirc-web-nginx-and-upstart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post I will cover how to start a NodeJS app (<code>lirc_web</code>) when a RaspberryPi boots up. This ensures that if the RaspberryPi ever loses power, the <code>lirc_web</code> app will restart when the system comes online. <code>lirc_web</code> is an open source NodeJS app I wrote as part of the <a href="http://opensourceuniversalremote.com">Open Source Universal Remote</a> project. If you'd like to learn more about the project, please check out <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures/">Open Source Universal Remote - Parts &amp; Pictures</a>.</p>

<p>To accomplish this will take three steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Configure the hostname for the RaspberryPi</li>
<li>Install and configure Upstart</li>
<li>Install and configure NGINX</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Note: Not all mobile devices support <code>.local</code> domains. You may still need to connect via IP.</strong></p>

<h3>Configure the hostname for the RaspberryPi</h3>

<p>If you want your RaspberryPi to be accessible on your local network via hostname, instead of always typing it's IP address, you'll want to install an mDNS daemon. If you'd like to learn why, I recommend reading <a href="http://www.howtogeek.com/167190/how-and-why-to-assign-the-.local-domain-to-your-raspberry-pi/">How (and Why) to Assign the .local Domain to Your Raspberry Pi</a>. The RaspberryPi supports Avahi, which can be installed with:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install avahi-daemon
</code></pre>

<p>When that finishes, try pinging <code>raspberrypi.local</code> from a different computer. Everything should just work. Next, we'll update the hostname of the RaspberryPi to be <code>universalremote</code>. This requires three steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Edit <code>/etc/hosts</code> and change the last line to <code>127.0.1.1 universalremote</code></li>
<li>Edit <code>/etc/hostname</code> and change the hostname to <code>universalremote</code></li>
<li>Reboot the RaspberryPi by running <code>sudo shutdown -r now</code></li>
</ol>


<p>After the RaspberryPi boots back up, you should be able to connect to the RaspberryPi via hostname (<code>http://universalremote.local</code>) or IP.</p>

<h3>Install and configure Upstart</h3>

<p>To ensure the <code>lirc_web</code> app starts when the RaspberryPi boots, we will use a tool called <a href="http://upstart.ubuntu.com">Upstart</a>. Upstart is a project from Ubuntu that simplifies writing init scripts. If you want to learn more about it, you can visit <a href="http://upstart.ubuntu.com/">http://upstart.ubuntu.com/</a> and read more. RaspbianOS does not include Upstart by default, but it can be installed to replace sysvinit with no negative consequences. Here are the commands:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install upstart
# You will be asked to type 'Yes, do as I say!'
# You may see an error about initctl being unable to connect, which will be fixed after a reboot

# Reboot the RaspberryPi
sudo shutdown -r now
</code></pre>

<p>Once the RaspberryPi reboots Upstart should be installed. Upstart configuration files are placed in <code>/etc/init</code>. You can either use the sample Upstart configuration that comes with the <code>lirc_web</code> Git repository, or you can use this example (place in <code>/etc/init/open-source-universal-remote.conf</code>):</p>

<pre><code># /etc/init/open-source-universal-remote.conf
description "universalremote.local"

start on runlevel [2345]
stop on runlevel [016]

# Restart when job dies
respawn

# Give up restart after 5 respawns in 60 seconds
respawn limit 5 60

script

  echo $$ &gt; /var/run/open-source-universal-remote.pid
  exec /usr/local/bin/node /home/pi/lirc_web/app.js 2&gt;&amp;1 &gt;&gt; /var/log/open-source-universal-remote.upstart.log

end script

pre-start script
    # Date format same as (new Date()).toISOString() for consistency
    echo "[`date -u +%Y-%m-%dT%T.%3NZ`] (sys) Starting" &gt;&gt; /var/log/open-source-universal-remote.upstart.log
end script

pre-stop script
    rm /var/run/open-source-universal-remote.pid
    echo "[`date -u +%Y-%m-%dT%T.%3NZ`] (sys) Stopping" &gt;&gt; /var/log/open-source-universal-remote.upstart.log
end script
</code></pre>

<p>After creating the Upstart script, you should be able to start the <code>lirc_web</code> project by running:</p>

<pre><code>sudo initctl start open-source-universal-remote
</code></pre>

<p>You can verify everything works by opening <code>http://universalremote.local:3000</code> (or the RaspberryPi's IP address) in your web browser. You should see the <code>lirc_web</code> web interface.</p>

<h3>Install and Configure NGINX</h3>

<p>If you run <code>lirc_web</code> by itself it creates a basic web server on port 3000. This is fine, but it's more convenient when an web application runs on port 80, the default port for web traffic. We'll use the free and open source NGINX web server to accomplish this.</p>

<p>To install nginx and ensure it starts on boot, run:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install nginx
update-rc.d nginx defaults
sudo service nginx start
</code></pre>

<p>When this completes, confirm everything installed correctly by trying to  access <code>http://universalremote.local</code> in your web browser. You should see a "Welcome to nginx!" web page.</p>

<p>Next, we have to configure nginx to serve the <code>lirc_web</code> app. You can use the sample config file included in the <code>lirc_web</code> Git repository (within the config directory), or use this example:</p>

<pre><code>server {
    listen            80;
    server_name       universalremote.local;

    # Change this to the location you installed lirc_web
    root              /home/pi/lirc_web;
    index             index.html index.htm;

    access_log        /var/log/open-source-universal-remote.nginx.log;

    location / {
        proxy_set_header X-Real-IP $remote_addr;
        proxy_set_header X-Forwarded-For $proxy_add_x_forwarded_for;
        proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
        proxy_set_header X-NginX-Proxy true;

        proxy_pass http://127.0.0.1:3000/;
        proxy_redirect off;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Update November 11th, 2013:</strong> Save this configuration data in a file called <code>/etc/nginx/conf.d/open-source-universal-remote.conf</code>. Nginx will automatically detect this file once you restart it.</p>

<p>Restart nginx to pick up the new configuration file with <code>sudo service nginx restart</code>.</p>

<p>Now, if you visit <code>http://universalremote.local</code> in your web browser you should now see the project running. In the future, any time you reboot the RaspberryPi <code>lirc_web</code> will start automatically.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>If everything went smoothly you should now have a daemonzized version of <code>lirc_web</code> running on your RaspberryPi, which is being served via nginx over port 80. In addition, any time you restart your RaspberryPi the <code>lirc_web</code> app will start up at boot.</p>

<p>Are you interested in reading more about the Open Source Universal Remote project? Check out:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/01/06/setting-up-lirc-on-the-raspberrypi/">Setting up LIRC on the RaspberryPi</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/02/23/controlling-lirc-from-the-web/">Controlling LIRC from the web</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/01/using-the-pebble-watch-to-control-your-home-theater/">Using a RaspberryPi and a Pebble Watch to control your home theater</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures/">Open Source Universal Remote - Parts &amp; Pictures</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lirc_web v0.0.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/08/21/lirc-web-v0-0-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-21T10:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2013/08/21/lirc-web-v0-0-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>August 10, 2014 Update:</strong> Latest version is now <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2014/08/10/lirc-web-v0-0-8/">lirc_web v0.0.8</a></p>

<p>I've updated the <code>lirc_web</code> project (available at <a href="http://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">http://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web</a>) to v0.0.5. This version fixes a bug related to the <a href="https://npmjs.org/package/swig">swig</a> npm module that was causing an error when trying to view the project in a browser.</p>

<p>If you were encountering a JavaScript error after trying to install <code>lirc_web</code> this should fix it. Thanks to the folks that reported this.</p>

<p>Please let me know if you encounter any other errors!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
