<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: electronics | alexba.in]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/categories/electronics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexba.in/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-14T05:14:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexba.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Bain]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alex@alexba.in]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Receiving SMS notifications from your washer & dryer]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2014/01/06/receiving-sms-notifications-from-your-washer/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T03:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2014/01/06/receiving-sms-notifications-from-your-washer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_pebble_notification.jpg" class="center" /></p>

<p>Previously, I discussed how I built an <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures/">open source universal remote</a> using a RaspberryPi, an expansion board, and a <a href="http://github.com/alexbain/lirc_web">NodeJS web application</a>. This device allows me to control any infrared device in my home from my phone, smart watch, laptop, or other web connected device. I use the remote daily, and it's sparked my curiosity to devise new ways of enhancing my environment with internet connected devices.</p>

<p>In this post, I'm going to cover a new project I recently finished - creating a device that monitors a washer or dryer and sends a text message when it detects that a load of laundry has finished. Beyond the novelty and simplicity of receiving a text message when the laundry is done, I built this device for two reasons. First, I wanted a project that introduced me to accelerometers - a sensor I've wanted to work with. Second, I wanted to take another stab at applying the principles of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_enhancement">progressive enhancement</a>, a web software concept, to the physical world.</p>

<blockquote><p>"Progressive enhancement uses web technologies in a layered fashion that allows everyone to access the basic content and functionality of a web page, [...] while also providing an enhanced version of the page to those with more advanced browser software [...]." (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_enhancement">Wikipedia</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>I wanted to see if I could apply the concept of progressive enhancement to the physical world by enhancing an existing appliance (in this case, a washer or dryer) with new digital functionality - without modifying it's existing form or interface. I wanted the appliance to look and behave exactly as it did before the modification, and I wanted no visual evidence that my device had been installed. After some brainstorming, I came up with an approach that met my goals. Read on to learn how I build it, and how you can build one yourself.</p>

<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_circuit_macro.jpg" class="center" /></p>

<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>At a high level, the project works as follows: a 3D printed enclosure magnetically attaches to the outside of the washer or dryer. Inside the enclosure is an <a href="http://electricimp.com">Electric Imp</a> microcontroller and an <a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/163">ADXL335 accelerometer</a>. The accelerometer measures the vibrations of the washer and dryer. The microcontroller has firmware on it that samples the accelerometer, processes the output, and periodically sends a computed result to a server in the cloud. The server receives the output and runs an algorithm that determines whether the washer or dryer is currently running. Once the server has confidently determined that the washer or dryer has finished running, it sends an SMS (using <a href="http://twilio.com">Twilio</a>) to one or more predefined phone numbers.</p>

<p>I'll cover the implementation in more detail below. This post is broken down into three sections:</p>

<ul>
<li>The hardware</li>
<li>The 3D printable enclosure</li>
<li>The software</li>
</ul>


<p>I'll end with a conclusion and some closing thoughts.</p>

<h2>Part 1: The Hardware</h2>

<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_hardware_device.jpg" class="center" /></p>

<p>For this project, I purchased most of my parts from <a href="http://adafruit.com">Adafruit</a>, an online retailer of electronic components. The rest of the parts I purchased from <a href="http://amazon.com">Amazon</a>. Here's the bill of materials:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/1129">Electric Imp</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/1130">April dev board for Electric Imp</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/163">ADXL335 analog 3.3V +-3g accelerometer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/589">Quarter size perma-proto breadboard</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/501">USB power supply</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/AmazonBasics-A-Male-Mini-B-Cable-Meters/dp/B001TH7GUK/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1388982594&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=usb+mini">USB A to Mini B cable</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/289">Solid core wire</a></li>
<li>2 small rare earth magnets (available from any hardware store)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Electric Imp</h3>

<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_electric_imp.jpg" class="center" /></p>

<p>For this project, I chose to work with the <a href="http://electricimp.com/product/">Electric Imp</a> microcontroller. The Electric Imp is a microcontroller in the form factor of an SD card with a 32bit Cortex M3 processor. What I find most interesting about the Electric Imp is that it also includes an 802.11b/g/n chip, making it one of the smallest WiFi enabled microcontrollers I've found. I also used the <a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/1130">April development board</a>, a breakout board from the Electric Imp team, which breaks out the pins on the imp and provides a mini USB connection for power. You can see that development board, a green circuit board, in the image beneath the "Hardware" header.</p>

<p>Configuring the Electric Imp with your WiFi credentials is done through a clever process called <a href="http://electricimp.com/product/blinkup/">BlinkUp</a>. The Imp itself contains a phototransistor, which enables you to program your WiFi credentials optically, via an app on your Android or iOS device. Once you install and configure the app, the display on your phone strobes in a pattern that the Imp recognizes, which programs the WiFi credentials into the Imp. The process only takes a few seconds, and it worked flawlessly for me the first time.</p>

<p>Once you've programmed your WiFi credentials onto the Imp, it will automatically connect to the Electric Imp cloud service. From there, you're able to login to the web based IDE and program the imp via your web browser. The IDE handles deploying code updates to the device, as well. I'd like to see a GitHub integration, which would provide version control, so hopefully that's on their roadmap.</p>

<h3>ADXL335 Analog Accelerometer</h3>

<p><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_adxl335.jpg" class="center" /></p>

<p>For the accelerometer (the component that measures the vibration of the washing machine / dryer), I chose the <a href="http://www.analog.com/static/imported-files/data_sheets/ADXL335.pdf">ADXL335</a>. The ADXL335 is a 3.3V analog accelerometer sensitive to +- 3g. The device itself is widely used, and I found plenty of documentation online. In addition, <a href="http://adafruit.com">Adafruit</a> sells a breakout board (listed above in the bill of materials) that made including the device in my project an easy decision. The breakout board that Adafruit sells also allows you to connect the accelerometer to a 5V microcontroller, such as an Arduino.</p>

<h3>Assembling the Hardware</h3>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/hardware_device_2.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_hardware_device_2.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>The assembly of the device is relatively straightforward. First, you will need to assemble the April development board and the ADXL335 breakout board by soldering the header pins onto the breakout boards. Next, you'll need to solder both breakout boards into the perma-proto board. Lastly, you'll solder in the 5 wires to enable the two components to communicate. <strong>If you intend to use the 3D printable enclosure, please ensure that the two components are mounted identically to the image above.</strong></p>

<p>The picture above shows how the device looks when assembled, and here are the specifics:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pin 1 from Electric Imp is connected to the X-out pin on accelerometer.</li>
<li>Pin 2 from the Electric Imp is connected to the Y-out pin on accelerometer.</li>
<li>Pin 5 from the Electric Imp is connected to the Z-out pin on accelerometer.</li>
<li>3V3 pin from Electric Imp is connected to the Vin pin on accelerometer.</li>
<li>GND pin from Electric Imp is connected to GND pin on accelerometer.</li>
</ul>


<p>At this point you should be able to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Boot the device up with a USB power supply</li>
<li>Program the Electric Imp to connect to your WiFi</li>
<li>Log into the Electric Imp web based IDE to program the device</li>
</ul>


<h2>Part 2: The 3D Printable Enclosure</h2>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/empty_case.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_empty_case.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>For this project, I wanted a custom enclosure that would enable the device to be sealed from dust and debris. I contacted a friend of mine, John Steenson, who agreed to help me design a 3D printable enclosure for the project. He has agreed to let me post the STL files for the case, which you can download and have 3D printed yourself. I had my case printed from a local printer that I found on the <a href="http://3dhubs.com">3D Hubs</a> service. I had a great experience with 3D Hubs, and highly suggest it if you're trying to find a local 3D printer.</p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/occupied_case.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_occupied_case.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/case_with_lid.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/lundry/thumb_case_with_lid.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>The above photos show the device mounted in the case (with and without the lid). Inside of the case, but beneath the device, I have attached (with two sided tape) the two rare earth magnets. I then placed a thin sheet of plastic between the magnets and the device to ensure there is no chance of electrical short. I have not found that the magnets interfere with the device in any way. The two magnets are what enables the device to attach to the washer or dryer.</p>

<p><strong>STL files for the 3D printable enclosure:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/stl/lundry/Enclosure_base.STL">Enclosure - Base</a></li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/stl/lundry/Enclosure_lid.STL">Enclosure - Lid</a></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Screws / nuts for mounting device within enclosure and securing lid:</strong></p>

<p>All part numbers are from <a href="http://www.mcmaster.com/">McMaster-Carr</a>. Per my friend John, quantities noted are the quantities required for assembly, not package quantity. You'll have some extra parts, but they'll probably come in handy for future projects down the road.</p>

<ul>
<li>3x - 91420A008</li>
<li>2x - 92000A015</li>
<li>2x - 93475A195</li>
<li>5x - 90592A004</li>
<li>1x - 8461K12 - Trim to fit</li>
</ul>


<h2>Part 3: Writing the Software</h2>

<p>When writing software for the Electric Imp, you write two programs. The first program, called the "Device", runs on the Electric Imp hardware. The second program, called the "Agent", runs on the Electric Imp cloud. The Agent has the ability to send and receive HTTP traffic, making it a perfect candidate for the Twilio API, a RESTful API that allows you to send SMS messages.</p>

<p>For this project, the Device samples the accelerometer 50x a second. I found this to be frequent enough to get a clear picture for how much the washer or dryer is vibrating. For each sample, I determine the magnitude of the accelerometer vector and compute the percentage of change against the previous sample's magnitude. I track the amount of change over 5 seconds (250 samples), and return that value to the Agent. In my testing, I found that the average reading when the machine was turned off to be between 100 and 250. When the washer or dryer are running, I find the samples vary between 275 and 6000 depending on what stage of the cycle the machine is in.</p>

<p>The Agent receives the total amount change over the past 250 samples, and compares that against a threshold to determine if the machine is ON or OFF. If the value is above the threshold, the device is experiencing enough vibration where it's safe to call the machine ON. In my testing, I found 280 to be a good threshold to determine if the washer or dryer was running. Once the Agent receives N consecutive samples above the threshold, it enters the RUNNING state. Then, at some point in the future, once the Agent receives M consecutive samples below the ON threshold, it returns to the OFF state. These delays help take into account lulls in vibration during a typical laundry cycle (ex: filling the washer, rinse cycle, draining the washer). Depending on your appliances, you may need to adjust the thresholds in the Agent to reduce false positives. Finally, when returning to the OFF state, if the device was in the RUNNING state, an SMS notification is emitted (via <a href="http://twilio.com">Twilio</a>) to each phone number stored in the <code>phoneNumbers</code> array.</p>

<p>If you'd like to read more about how to process the data coming off an accelerometer, I found <a href="http://www.starlino.com/imu_guide.html">A Guide To using IMU (Accelerometer and Gyroscope Devices) in Embedded Applications</a> to be an extremely informative read.</p>

<p><strong> Note:</strong> The Agent code requires you to setup a Twilio account and enter your Twilio credentials before you can send any messages. Twilio, at the time of writing this article, charges $0.01 per text message. At the rate I do laundry, it should cost &lt; $2 a year to send these text messages.</p>

<p><strong>Note2:</strong> If you would like to log all of your data to a persistent data store (either to show on a web page, or just to analyze output), <a href="http://firebase.com">Firebase</a> is a great option, and they have a free tier. Just change <code>logToFirebase</code> to be <code>true</code> and enter your Firebase URL if you want to enable this feature.</p>

<p>You may also <a href="https://gist.github.com/alexbain/8392153">view this code</a> on GitHub.</p>

<p>Here is the code for the Device, which reads in and processes the accelerometer data:</p>

<pre><code>total &lt;- 0; // Sum of % change from all samples
n &lt;- 0;     // Counter for number of samples read
last &lt;- 1;  // Previous reading of magnitude

function readSensor() {
    // Time interval
    local interval = 0.02;

    // Get source voltage, should be 3.3V
    local vRef = hardware.voltage();

    // Read in ADC values from accelerometer
    local adcRx = hardware.pin1.read();
    local adcRy = hardware.pin2.read();
    local adcRz = hardware.pin5.read();
    // server.log(format("Raw ADC values: %f, %f, %f", adcRx, adcRy, adcRz));

    // Convert 16bit ADC accelerometer values (0-65535) into voltage
    local voltsRx = (adcRx * vRef) / 65535.0;
    local voltsRy = (adcRy * vRef) / 65535.0;
    local voltsRz = (adcRz * vRef) / 65535.0;
    // server.log(format("Voltages: %f, %f %f", voltsRx, voltsRy, voltsRz));

    // Subtract 0g (1.5V at 3V, 1.65V at 3.3V)
    local deltaVoltsRx = voltsRx - (vRef / 2);
    local deltaVoltsRy = voltsRy - (vRef / 2);
    local deltaVoltsRz = voltsRz - (vRef / 2);
    // server.log(format("Adjusted voltages %f, %f, %f", deltaVoltsRx, deltaVoltsRy, deltaVoltsRz));

    // Convert from voltage to g, using sensitivity of 300mV
    local rX = deltaVoltsRx / 0.3;
    local rY = deltaVoltsRy / 0.3;
    local rZ = deltaVoltsRz / 0.3;
    // server.log(format("Gs: %f, %f, %f", rX, rY, rZ));

    // Compute magnitude of force
    local magnitude = math.sqrt(math.pow(rX,2) + math.pow(rY, 2) + math.pow(rZ, 2));

    // Compute % change since last reading
    local change = math.fabs((magnitude - last)/last) * 100.0;

    // Store magnitude in last for next time
    last = magnitude;

    // Log magnitude and percent change
    // server.log(format("magnitude: %f, change amount: %f", magnitude, change));

    // Increment total with % change, increment N
    total = total + change;
    n = n + 1;

    // Log data to server once ever 250 samples (5 seconds)
    if (n &gt;= 250) {
        agent.send("data", total);
        n = 0;
        total = 0;
    }

    // Sleep until time to read sensor again
    imp.wakeup(interval, readSensor);
}

// X input
hardware.pin1.configure(ANALOG_IN);

// Y input
hardware.pin2.configure(ANALOG_IN);

// Z input
hardware.pin5.configure(ANALOG_IN);

// Start reading the sensor
readSensor();
</code></pre>

<p>Here is the code for the Agent, which determines when to send an SMS</p>

<pre><code>// Run on Agent

// Thresholds to adjust for better accuracy
dataThreshold &lt;- 280; // Minimum accelerometer value to count as ON
onThreshold &lt;- 24;    // Number of ON samples before machine enters RUNNING state
offThreshold &lt;- 60;   // Number of OFF samples before machine enters OFF state

// State variable
running &lt;- false;

// Keep track of counts
onCount &lt;- 0;
offCount &lt;- 0;

// Twilio
twilioURL &lt;- "https://USER:PASS@api.twilio.com/2010-04-01/Accounts/ID/Messages.json";
twilioHeaders &lt;- { "Content-Type": "application/x-www-form-urlencoded" };
twilioNumber &lt;- "+14155551212";

// Array of phone numbers to be contacted with the laundry is done
phoneNumbers &lt;- ["+14155555555", "+14155555556"];

// Firebase
logToFirebase &lt;- false;
firebaseURL &lt;- "https://FIREBASE_URL.firebaseIO.com/data.json";
firebaseHeaders &lt;- { "Content-Type": "application/json" };

// Called every time the imp emits data
device.on("data", function(data) {

    // Is there enough accelerometer activity for the device to be considered ON?
    if (data &gt;= dataThreshold) {
        onCount = onCount + 1;

        // Prevent overflow errors by resetting onCount when it gets close to limit
        if (onCount &gt;= 65500) {
            onCount = onThreshold;
        }

        // If the device has been ON for long enough, set running state to be true
        if (onCount &gt;= onThreshold) {
            running = true;

            // Running, so reset offCount
            offCount = 0;
        }

        // debug / logs
        if (running == true) {
            server.log(format("ON - RUNNING (%f), onCount (%d), offCount (%d)", data, onCount, offCount));
        } else {
            server.log(format("ON (%f), onCount (%d), offCount (%d)", data, onCount, offCount));
        }

    // Imp is not recording much accelerometer movement, so device seems to be OFF
    } else {
        offCount = offCount + 1;

        // Prevent overflow errors by resetting offCount when it gets close to limit
        if (offCount &gt;= 65500) {
            offCount = offThreshold;
        }

        // Has the device been off for long enough to be "done"?
        if (offCount &gt;= offThreshold) {

            // Was the device previously running?
            if (running == true) {

                // This means that the laundry had been running, and is now done.

                // Send an SMS to each phone number in the phoneNumbers array.
                foreach (number in phoneNumbers) {
                    local body = format("To=%s&amp;From=%s&amp;Body=The%%20laundry%%20is%%20done.", number, twilioNumber);
                    local request = http.post(twilioURL, twilioHeaders, body);
                    local response = request.sendasync(function(done) {});
                }

                // debug / logs
                server.log("!!!! Emitting OFF event !!!!");
            }

            // Reset on count
            onCount = 0;

            // Machine is no longer running
            running = false;
        }

        // debug / logs
        if (running == true) {
            server.log(format("OFF - WAS RUNNING (%f), onCount (%d), offCount (%d)", data, onCount, offCount));
        } else {
            server.log(format("OFF (%f), onCount (%d), offCount (%d)", data, onCount, offCount));
        }
    }

    if (logToFirebase == true) {
        // Build a post request to Firebase to log the data
        local body = format("{\"amount\": %f, \"running\": %s, \".priority\": %d}", data, running ? "true" : "false", time());
        local request = http.post(firebaseURL, firebaseHeaders, body);

        // Send the data to Firebase async
        local response = request.sendasync(function(done) {});
    }
});
</code></pre>

<p>After loading these two pieces of software onto the Electric Imp (via the web IDE), you should be ready to install the device in your home! Installation is simple - just magnetically attach the device to any metal service on the washer or dryer. Give it a whirl by doing a load of laundry and watching the log files (via the web IDE). If all goes well, you should receive a text message a few minutes after the load of laundry completes.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I set out to build a minimally invasive device that progressively enhanced an appliance into the digital age, which didn't physically modify the appliance in any way. During the project I had the opportunity to work with a few new technologies - the Electric Imp, an accelerometer, and 3D printing. All in all, I'd say the project was a success. The device is currently hooked up to my washer, and it works well in it's current state.</p>

<p>This project came out of a (relatively) trivial need - to know when a load of laundry is done when you aren't in close proximity to the washer or dryer. I thought it would be clever to receive a text message when the laundry is done, since all phones support SMS and Twilio has made interacting with SMS easy. This also gets around the need to download or install a native app on your phone.</p>

<p>I do recognize there are other approaches to solving this problem - monitoring the power output of the appliance, listening for the buzzer with a microphone, or placing a photodiode over a "done" indicator - but I ultimately chose the accelerometer because I wanted to gain experience working with the sensor.</p>

<p>While I do not believe I'll be spending much additional time on this project, there are a number of potential enhancements that I see:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adding a battery, to make the device portable.</li>
<li>Swapping out a WiFi chip for a GSM chip, allowing you to take the device to a laundromat.</li>
<li>Designing a custom circuit board, to dramatically reduce the size of the device.</li>
<li>Creating a waterproof (and heat tolerant) device/enclosure so you can place the device inside the washer/dryer. This would be more secure than leaving a device on top of a machine.</li>
</ul>


<p>Hopefully you found this post helpful if you're trying to implement a similar device yourself. If you have any questions, feel free to ask in the comments. If you're interested in having one of these devices for yourself, but don't want to build one, send me an email at <a href="mailto:alex@alexba.in">alex@alexba.in</a> and we can work something out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Source Universal Remote - Parts &amp; Pictures]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T16:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2013/06/08/open-source-universal-remote-parts-and-pictures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_installed.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_installed.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>This past weekend I converted my <a href="http://opensourceuniversalremote.com">Open Source Universal Remote</a> breadboard layout into a more permanent soldered circuit. I used the <a href="http://octopart.com/ada801-adafruit+industries-27056076">Adafruit Protoboard</a> as a base instead of having a custom circuit board printed, which worked out well. The protoboard is perfectly sized for the RaspberryPi and I highly recommend it for any RaspberryPi related hardware projects.</p>

<p>Below, I've attached some high resolution photographs of the finished protoboard (front and back). I've also created separate versions of the photographs which are fully annotated and explain how all of the components are laid out. Please note that I did make one miscalculation in my circuit which I have corrected with a yellow jumper wire. I've pointed out the miscalculation on both annotated photographs.</p>

<h3>Parts list:</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/ada801-adafruit+industries-27056076">1 Adafruit RaspberryPi Protoboard</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/ir333c-everlight-17677690">2 940nm 40deg IR LEDs</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/hlmp-5029-avago-549484">2 right angle LED holders</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/p2n2222ag-on+semiconductor-358561">1 P2N2222AGOD-ND transistor</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/od103je-ohmite-133027">1 10k Ohm resistor</a></li>
<li><a href="http://octopart.com/tsop38238-vishay-11814552">1 TSOP38238 38KHz IR receiver</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.adafruit.com/products/1311">Hook-up Wire Spool Set - 22AWG Solid Core - 6 x 25 ft</a></li>
<li>RaspberryPi running LIRC (See: <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/01/04/raspberrypi-quickstart/">RaspberryPi Quickstart</a>, <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/01/06/setting-up-lirc-on-the-raspberrypi/">Setting Up LIRC on the RaspberryPi</a>, <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/01/15/installing-nodejs-on-your-raspberrypi/">Installing NodeJS on your RaspberryPi</a>, and <a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/02/23/controlling-lirc-from-the-web/">Controlling LIRC from the Web</a>)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Schematic:</h3>

<p><a href="http://upverter.com/alexbain/f24516375cfae8b9/Open-Source-Universal-Remote/#/"><img src="http://upverter.com/alexbain/f24516375cfae8b9/Open-Source-Universal-Remote/embed_img/13715285520000/" alt="Open Source Universal Remote by alexbain f24516375cfae8b9 - Upverter" /></a></p>

<h3>Project pictures:</h3>

<p>All pictures link to a full resolution image (10+ megapixel) which provides plenty of additional resolution for examining the circuit. The annotated photographs should help fill in anything that is unclear. If you have any questions, please leave them in the comments.</p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_top.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_top.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_top_annotated.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_top_annotated.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_bottom.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_bottom.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_bottom_annotated.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_bottom_annotated.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_installed_alt.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_installed_alt.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/protoboard_v1_installed_back.jpg"><img src="http://alexba.in/images/posts/protoboard_v1/thumb_protoboard_v1_installed_back.jpg" class="center" /></a></p>

<p>If you'd like to read more about this project, here is some further reading:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/03/06/open-source-universal-remote/">Open Source Universal Remote intro</a> - Intro post to the project</li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/03/09/raspberrypi-ir-schematic-for-lirc/">RaspberryPi IR Schematic for LIRC</a> - Electrical schematic for the hardware</li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/01/06/setting-up-lirc-on-the-raspberrypi/">Setting up LIRC on the RaspberryPi</a> - Installing and configuring IR software</li>
<li><a href="http://alexba.in/blog/2013/02/23/controlling-lirc-from-the-web/">Controlling LIRC From the Web</a> - Installing (mobile/desktop) web interface</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Universal remote experiments]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexba.in/blog/2012/07/08/universal-remote-experiments/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-08T09:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexba.in/blog/2012/07/08/universal-remote-experiments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few months I've decided to teach myself a bit about embedded
microcontrollers and electronics. I've never worked with hardware before and,
after a bit of Googling, found an amazing Maker / Open Hardware movement going
on that I could leverage to help bootstrap my ideas.</p>

<p>Since I've found the best way to motivate myself is with a concrete project I
decided that, for my first project, I wanted to build a universal remote that I
could control from my phone. I have a Harmony remote, which I use regularly,
but it's limited by line of sight and requires customization through a
cumbersome software interface.</p>

<p>My initial requirements were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Must be small enough to place discreetly in the room</li>
<li>Must be WiFi enabled</li>
<li>Must have great IR range and coverage</li>
<li>Must be able to learn existing commands</li>
<li>Must have a responsive web interface</li>
</ul>


<h4>Version 1: Arduino</h4>

<p>The first prototype I built was using an <a href="http://arduino.cc">Arduino Uno</a> microcontroller along with
<a href="http://www.arcfn.com/2009/08/multi-protocol-infrared-remote-library.html">Ken Shirriff's</a> multi protocol IR library. I had wired a 940nm IR LED to one
of the Arduino's pins and was able to get about two feet of range out of it.</p>

<p>Next, I extended the code and attached a <a href="http://www.sparkfun.com/products/10822">Roving Networks RN-XV</a> WiFi chip to
my project so it was WiFi enabled. So far so good. I could now send or receive
IR commands (relatively well, it wasn't perfect) over Wifi with about a two foot
range for the IR signal. I also had to hard code the WiFi credentials which meant
the device wasn't very portable, but at least it worked. This was version 1.1.</p>

<p>Version 1.2 was an updated hardware schematic that added a 2N2222 transistor to
the mix. Using a transistor meant that the output from the Arduino's pin was not
trying to power the LED but just telling a transitor to switch current on and off.
Since the transistor switches current significantly better than the output
pin of the Arduino I was able to extend the range for the IR blaster to about 15ft.
This change was inspired by open source schematics like <a href="http://www.ladyada.net/images/tvbgone/schematic.jpg">TV-B-Gone</a>.</p>

<p>Version 1.3 was to be the version with the web interface. This was where I realized
the limitations of the Arduino platform. I could not easily run a WiFi libray,
an IR library, and a web server off of an 8bit micro controller. I simply didn't
have the resources.</p>

<p>I had considered a few alternatives:</p>

<ul>
<li>Run a webserver on my laptop and just send commands to/from the Arduino</li>
<li>Run a webserver on the internet and relay commands that way</li>
<li>Purchase a device like a <a href="http://raspberrypi.org/">RaspberryPi</a> or <a href="http://beagleboard.org/bone/">Beaglebone</a> and run the web
server on that device. Communicate with the Arduino perhaps via XBee or over WiFi.</li>
</ul>


<p>Ultimately I decided that adding a second device increased the complexity of the
project beyond what I wanted. So, I scrapped the idea of using an Arduino and I'm
starting over with a <a href="http://raspberrypi.org/">RaspberryPi</a>.</p>

<h4>Version 2: RaspberryPi</h4>

<p>The <a href="http://raspberrypi.org/">RaspberryPi</a> is a completely different beast than the <a href="http://arduino.cc">Arduino</a>. The <a href="http://raspberrypi.org/">RaspberryPi</a>
is about as powerful as a mobile phone. It's got an ARM processor,
ethernet port, RAM, SD card for storage, and a bunch of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Purpose_Input/Output">GPIO</a> pins for a hardware
interface.</p>

<p>So first up was finding an IR software package (designed for a Linux OS) that
could handle the transmission and receiving of IR signals. This lead me to
<a href="http://www.lirc.org/">LIRC</a> - the Linux Infrared Remote Control project. This project has been
around for a while, has a bunch of hardware schematics available (sending and
receiving) for it, and is open source. Perfect.</p>

<p>This lead me to getting LIRC working on my RaspberryPi. Luckily a chap who goes
by the name <a href="http://aron.ws/projects/lirc_rpi/">ar0n</a> has already opened a <a href="https://github.com/raspberrypi/linux/pull/38">pull request</a> that adds preliminary
LIRC support to the RaspberryPi linux kernel.</p>

<p>So, at this very moment, I am attempting to recompile the RaspberryPi linux kernel
with LIRC support. Once this step is done I'll wire up some hardware to test
sending and receiving. Once that works I should be back to "adding a web platform"
which will be significantly easier when powered by an entire Linux stack.</p>

<p>I'll post another update down the road once I've gotten this step working.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
